Loujon Press collection, 1962-1965
University of Arizona Libraries, Special Collections
Loujon Press Collection, 1962-1965
MS 291
Loujon Press
This collection is comprised of six series: Historical notes, 1989. Correspondence, 1962-1965. Notebook, 1964. Photographs, ca. 1962-1965. Artwork, ca. 1963-1965. Book Files, 1963-1965. It includes correspondence, poetry manuscripts, a notebook, galley proofs, production materials, drawings, and photographs relating to Charles Bukowski. Specific material regards his collaboration with Jon Webb in the creation of two poetry books for Loujon Press.
1.25 linear feet
University of Arizona Libraries, Special Collections University of Arizona PO Box 210055 Tucson, AZ 85721-0055 Phone: 520-621-6423 Fax: 520-621-9733 URL: http://speccoll.library.arizona.edu/
Restrictions
None.
Accurals by purchase
Historical Note
After working as free-lance editors in New York City, Jon and Gypsy Lou Webb moved to New Orleans. There they produced an avant-garde poetry and prose magazine, The Outsider (1961-), for American "underground" writers. Pouring all their money and energy into their letterpress Loujon Press, they designed and produced several limited editions of works by Charles Bukowski and Henry Miller from 1963 until 1966. In 1965, the Webbs moved to Santa Fe, El Paso, and settled for a while at 1009 E. Elm in Tucson. They later moved the press to 1202 Fourth S.W. in Albuquerque. Jon Webb died in Nashville on June 9, 1971. His obituaries are cited in AB Bookman's Weekly, August 2, 1971.
Organization
This collection is organized into six series:
Series I: Historical Notes, 1989
Series II: Correspondence, 1962-1965
Series III: Notebook, 1964
Series IV: Photographs, circa. 1962-1997
Series V: Artwork, circa. 1963-1965
Series VI: Book Files, 1963-1965
Scope and Content Note
This collection provides insights chiefly into writer Charles Bukowski's daily life in Los Angeles, California from late 1962 to summer 1965. The correspondence, over two hundred letters from him to Webb, are filled with prime Bukowski narration of hard drinking, bad luck at the horse races, neurotic neighbors, demanding landlords, reflections on writing and other poets, his daytime jobs, his enthusiasm for the efforts of Jon and "Gypsy" Louise Webb and their Loujon Press, and a myriad of other topics. Some letters are written or appended with notes from Frances Bukowski about the current state of things in their lives as they lived on North Mariposa Avenue and later De Longpre, including the birth and infancy of their daughter, Marina Louise. Bukowski's satisfaction with the wonder of It Catches My Heart in Its Hands is candidly portrayed in his letter of November 26, 1963.
By 1964, Bukowski begins to draw, paste, and color the marginalia of the letters and envelopes. Collages of bubble-gum cartoons and cigar bands are pasted on ink, water-colors and scraps of paper while his messages scroll around and between the drawings. The typewritten letters are no more, Bukowski is headed for the big time, and the Webbs and Loujon Press have provided him with two marvelous books as passport portfolios.
Additional letters are from John William Corrington to Webb, and from Webb to Bukowski. There are also a large file of letters of praise for It Catches My Heart in Its Hands from admirers including Lawrence Ferlinghetti, Kenneth Patchen, Henry Miller, and Walter Lowenfels.
A notebook by Bukowski contains 58 pages of handwritten, mostly unpublished poems, and includes a three page commentary on the contemporary state of poetry titled, "A depressing state of affairs...."
The photographs in the collection contain ten of Bukowski, one of his dog, three of the Webbs in their apartment/studio at 1109 Royal, New Orleans, and three of the Tucson residence at 1009 E. Elm as it appeared in 1997. There is also color and ink drawings by Bukowski, including five self-portraits. Some of the photographs and drawings were done for possible inclusion in the poetry books.
The manuscript files relating to the two books contain handwritten and typewritten poems by Bukowski (some with corrections), production materials, galleys, dummys, tearsheets from other poetry books of his poems, and related materials, such as biographical and exhibition materials relating to Noel Rockmore who created etchings for Crucifix in a Deathhand.
Access Terms
Bukowski, Charles -- Archives
Webb, Jon Edgar
Webb, Louise
Rockmore, Noel, 1928-
Loujon Press -- Archives
Small presses -- Louisiana -- 20th century
Poets, American -- 20th century -- Archival resources
Publishers and publishing -- Louisiana
Correspondence
Photographs
Poems
Drawings
Container List
- Series I: Historical Notes, 1989
  Chronology and narrative by Edwin Blair on the Webbs, Loujon Press, and Bukowski.
  - Historical notes, also marked up copies of Flower, Fist and Bestial Wail (1960), Run with the Hunted (1962), Longshot Poems for Broke Players (1962), and Poems and Drawings (Epos issue: 1962). Some included inscriptions to Webb from Bukowski, and some were partially dissected by Webb for use in designing his publications. 1989 (Box 1, Folder 1)
- Series II: Correspondence, 1962-1965
  Handwritten and typewritten, chiefly from Bukowski to Webb.
  - Bukowski to Webb. 1962-1965 (Box 1, Folder 2-9)
  - John William Corrington to Webb. 1963-1964 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Webb to Bukowski. 1963 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - To Webb from admirers of It Catches My Heart in Its Hands. 1963-1965 (Box 1, Folder 12)
- Series III: Notebook, 1964
  Handwritten poems and commentary by Bukowski.
  - Notebook. 1964 (Box 1, Folder 13)
- Series IV: Photographs, ca. 1962-1997
  Ten of Bukowski, one of his dog, three of the Webbs, three of residence at 1009 East Elm Street, Tucson (1997), eight photographs of the Webbs on a trip to Las Vegas; and one of the Webbs in Slidell, LA.
  - Photographs. ca. 1962-1997 (Box 1, Folder 14)
- Series V: Artwork, circa. 1962-1965
  Drawings and self-portraits on paper.
  - Drawings. circa. 1962-1965 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Envelopes. circa. 1962-1965 (Box 1, Folder 16)
- Series VI: Book Files, 1963-1965
  Typescripts and handwritten prose and poetry, some with corrections, and production materials relating to the titles.
  - It Catches My Heart in Its Hands, 1963
    - Introduction by John William Corrington. 1963 (Box 2, Folder 1)
    - Poems, some on tearsheets, by Bukowski. 1963 (Box 2, Folder 2-3)
    - Production materials. 1963 (Box 2, Folder 4)
    - Galleys. 1963 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Crucifix in a Deathhand, 1965
    - Poems. 1965 (Box 2, Folder 6)
    - Production materials. 1965 (Box 2, Folder 7)
    - Galleys and dummy. 1965 (Box 2, Folder 8-9)
    - Biographical information and exhibition catalogs on Noel Rockmore, artist. 1965 (Box 2, Folder 10)
- Correspondence, 1964-2000
  By creator, and thereunder chronological
  Handwritten and typewritten, chiefly from Jon and Lou Webb to Blair.
  Accession from Edwin Blair
  - Webb to Blair, 1964-1971 (Box 3, Folder 1-7)
  - Lou Webb to Blair, 1971-2000 (Box  3, Folder 8-21)
  - Miscellaneous to Blair, 1993-2000 (Box 3, Folder 22)
  - Lou Webb to Blair, No Dates (Box 3, Folder 23)
  - Webbs to Mike, 5/14/1971 (Box 3, Folder 24)
  - Poem: To Louise from Jon (Box 3, Folder 25)
- Loujon Press Administration, 1964-1988
  By type, and thereunder chronological
  Bank Statements, Contracts, Fundraising and Promotional Materials
  - Bank Statements, Canceled Checks, Contracts, 1963-1988 (Box 3, Folder 26)
  - Fundraising Letter, 1967 (Box 3, Folder 27)
  - Promotional Materials, 1967-1970 (Box 3)